AI is coming to consumer technology like
water running downhill.
>> This is Bobby Holly. He grew from an
intern to the CTO of Mozilla Firefox and
lived through the browser wars with
Google.
>> Every time Google would do something
that would hurt Firefox, it would always
be framed as unintentional.
>> He also had interesting stories from his
projects, including some difficult
security bugs he tackled.
>> I was disassembling it and then I had
this realization that like I knew who
had written this exploit. How'd you know
that that security researcher wrote that
vulnerability? He shared tips helpful
for any career in tech.
>> One thing that I think that everybody
can work on at whatever level they are
is writing and I think it is one of the
most powerful things.
>> There's this new era of browser wars
bringing AI into existing browsers.
>> I have pretty strong opinions about
this. Here's the full episode.
Before actually working at Firefox, I
saw that you you interned at Nvidia. I'm
kind of curious, why did you pick
Mozilla over Nvidia?
>> Yeah. So, I mean, my first internship
after freshman year was at NVIDIA. And
it was it was a great internship. Um, I
think it was much more uh standard of an
internship. you know, you show up, there
was orientation, they showed you what to
do, you sat at your desk, gave you a
very basic starter project, said, "Well,
you know, we'll check on you in a couple
hours." Um, and it was really designed
to be a sort of thoughtful, you know,
growing experience for somebody who
didn't really know what they were doing.
And Mosilla was, I would say, quite
different from that. Um, I remember
showing up uh really I think on my first
day. My manager was the director of
platform who ran all of Gecko. It was
this guy Damon Secor. Um, and he really
he had a very particular vibe. Um, he
sort of embodied I think the dude from
the big labowski in like all of the best
ways. Like just extremely laid-back. Um,
and I remember asking him, you know,
what should I work on? and he was like,
I don't know, like go get on IRC and get
on BugZilla and like start figuring out
some things to do. And that was just a
very big contrast to the sort of more
standard internship. And what that spoke
to was the nature of how Mozilla
operated because Mozilla had been an,
you know, open- source project that
largely happened in some ways by
accident where lots of people just
showed up and started working on things
and there was not a lot of support and
there was, you know, this was like way
before video conferencing. There was
just the bare minimum of what you needed
if you were really dedicated and really
um creative and really persistent to
figure out like how you would download
the code. You had to figure out how to
download it. You have to figure out how
to build it. You had to figure out where
to go to, you know, file bugs and like
get help. And there was just like not a
lot of guardrails. And what that
selected for was a particular type of
person um who really just needed the
bare minimum and was very motivated to
just go in and figure things out. And so
the management structure at the time was
very much oriented towards nurturing and
empowering this culture, right? Very
much like let's get the right people
together and let's just get out of the
way. And so this for me I would say
initially was a little bit disorienting
but I ended up getting really inspired
by all of the people who were working on
it. Some of whom were paid, some of whom
were not paid. And a lot of these
people, you know, maybe they'd started
being paid recently as Mozilla started
to have money, but had been, you know,
getting involved in the project from
their college dorm room just trying to
figure out how to make their browser
crash less. There was this guy um sort
of one of my longtime heroes, Boris
Sabarski. Uh we didn't really I didn't
think don't think there were really
titles at the time, but he eventually
was one of Mozilla's first distinguished
engineers. And he was just very awe
inspiring to me because I only, you
know, for I think several years I only
met him on IRC. But Mozilla was a wild
west, you know, the Firefox codebase was
a wild west of code just like tens, you
know, millions and millions, probably
about 10 million lines of code that were
inherited from Netscape and largely
unowned. And the major challenge was
just dealing with all of this code and
figuring it out. And Boris probably
owned like half of it. He was the person
of last resort that you would always ask
if you didn't know what to do. And you
would realize that you'd be having this
conversation with him on IRC. And for
me, it would be like taking all of my
focus of trying to understand and like,
you know, keep up with him. And then I
would realize that he was in like five
other channels at the same time, like
having these conversations with like
other senior Mozilla engineers, other
interns, contributors, users who were
just having bugs. And he was just a
machine.
So I'm kind of curious at this time, how
does this tie into the the timeline of
Google Chrome and and the browser wars?
Was this before Google Chrome?
>> Yeah, so this was before Chrome. Um I
guess as a brief history lesson, so the
original round of the browser wars was
in the '90s and this was largely defined
by Internet Explorer versus Netscape. Um
and they competed with each other by
trying to, you know, ship different
proprietary APIs and make the site work
better in IE or work better in in
Netscape. But eventually uh Internet
Explorer won largely because Microsoft
bundled it for free as part of Windows
um and was very aggressive with respect
to distribution and really pushing
Netscape out of distribution and
Microsoft eventually was you know taken
to court and lost and you know had an
antitrust judgment about precisely this
but the way the market works right like
it didn't matter like IE had already won
and Netscape was going under and as as
sort of a as a parting not they open
sourced the code um and created this
Mozilla Foundation to steward this
gargantuan mess of browser code that was
Nescape Navigator. And
then what happened was that Microsoft
decided that this web thing was not
particularly aligned with the strategic
interests of Microsoft, right? Because
this web thing was a new platform where
you could use the same have the same
experience across different operating
systems. And so they largely just
declared that they had won and they put
the browser in maintenance mode. But
there were a lot of people who really
saw the potential of what the web could
be and what it already was with like
Internet Explorer 5 and Internet
Explorer 6, but that it could be so much
more. And a lot of these people like
Boris were just drawn to I want to make
this experience better and I want my
browser to stop crashing. And so people
started downloading this source code for
Netscape Navigator and working on it and
gradually improving it and adding um new
features like the ability to block
pop-ups and the ability to have browser
tabs rather than a new window for every
website. And this sort of gradually
turned into um a really more useful
browser than Internet Explorer was. But
it was still very much a suite, right?
It had an email client in it. It had a
address book. It even had an IRC client
for all of the developers. You know, it
was kind of built into the browser so
they could talk to each other. And
eventually a few I think relatively
junior people, you know, just like some,
you know, contributors, interns, you
know, came along and decided to build
the stripped down version of it. And
that was originally um that was just a
browser, the bare minimum of what you
need for a browser. And that originally
they called it Phoenix, but then that
was a BIOS. Then they renamed it
Firebird, but that turned out to be a
database. And then finally they called
it Firefox. And Firefox just took off
like wildfire because the world really
wanted a better browser and it was a
better browser. And so Firefox became,
you know, just this thing that
everybody, you know, the first thing you
do when you got a computer, what you do
for all your friends, what you do for
your family members is install Firefox
because it's just such a better
experience. And Google was extremely um
well lined with this, right? because
Google was this, you know, burgeoning
product and business that was largely
built around a search engine that was
about discoverability of the web. And so
that the more that the web was
discoverable and usable and useful, the
better it was for Google. And Google
quickly realized that Internet Explorer
was a big problem and that Firefox was
really this coming solution uh to this.
And so Google was very um very invested
in Firefox's success. When I started as
an intern, we all received badges to go
over to the Google campus and eat lunch
whenever we wanted. There were snacks in
the kitchen that I heard I never quite
confirmed were directly delivered um by
the Google facilities people. And of
course, the most important was that
Google uh signed a deal with Mozilla to
be the default search engine for
Firefox. And this was perfectly fine
with Mozilla because everybody liked to
use Google anyway. And this was a great
uh user experience. And it also suddenly
allowed Mozilla to be financially
sustainable and to hire a lot of these
contributors who'd basically been
working nights and weekends. And Google
had engineers uh that were directly
working on Firefox and contributing to
it. And there was really this sense that
Google and Mozilla together were working
to unlock, you know, the future of the
open web.
And when I started in June of 2008, that
was sort of the peak of that sentiment.
But shortly thereafter, Google announced
that they were building their own
browser, which was Google Chrome. And I
think that you can obviously see why in
retrospect, right? The real the the
business strategic
posture of Google as a company was
really hinging on this ragtag group of
very weird people who were working on
this open source browser. And there was
a desire to have a little bit more
control over their own destiny. And so
when they initially announced Chrome,
you know, we had a a meeting. John Lily
told everybody who worked at Mozilla
about this, but indicated that it was
still very friendly. The desire was to
take market share away from Internet
Explorer and that we would still
continue to be close partners and on the
same side. And initially it really did
feel that way. Um, but as time went on
things started to change. And I think um
I think it was like 2009 there was a New
York Times article that I think really
captured the zeitgeist. I think the
title of it was something like between
Mozilla and Google group hugs are
getting tricky. And that referred to
this very positive hippie atmosphere of
working together on the future of the
open web and the degree to which
Google's more direct business interest
in owning and controlling the user's
journey on the web was starting to
create tension.
>> You mentioned that at some point you had
Google badges and you had free food
through Google and you had a good
working relationship with them. How did
it transition from that to a full
competition in your personal experience?
So my sense is that
as time went on things changed slowly
and I really don't think that it's a
situation where any individual person at
Google was like haha now we are going to
get them and they don't know but it's
just the way that organizations work and
so we continued to have strong
collaboration um with many engineers
over at Google but there were two things
that really happened at the same time
the first is that
Google really ramped up its attempt to
acquire market share with Chrome and
this was,
you know,
probably very truthfully aimed at
Internet Explorer, but Mozilla was very
much collateral damage and they were
spending hundreds of millions of dollars
a year on advertising and distribution.
And if you were to include the effective
cost of the advertising that they put on
google.com, which was their own
homepage,
the advertising spend, I think, would
reach into the billions. And there was
very much a sense that whenever we
talked to them that it wasn't supposed
to be directed at us. Jonathan
Nightingale who was a VP of uh Firefox
at the time, you know, a couple years
ago he did a, you know, a tweet thread
explaining his point of view on this and
I think he referred to it as the year of
100 oopses where every time Google would
do something that would hurt Firefox, it
would always be framed as unintentional,
right? And the obvious way this would be
is that like Firefox was sending source
traffic over to Google. And so when
users were in Firefox, they type
something in the address bar, they would
end up on Google. And then Google would
show these Firefox users an an ad that
would say or a big banner directly on
google.com, like not even on the search
result page saying, "Download Chrome.
It's better." And they always claimed
that it was unintentional, but these
things just kept happening over and
over. And I do think that on a sort of
organizational strategic level, it was
unintentional. But the individual
incentives of the people involved and
what they got by doing this and then you
know maybe fixing it in a in a release a
couple weeks later you know they still
won as far as their metrics were
concerned. So that was one piece, but
there was definitely another piece where
Firefox
had legitimately fallen behind. And part
of this was that when Chrome came out,
it had a lot of really interesting and
new architectural innovations um that
created gaps with Firefox. Some of these
included having a multipprocess
architecture um and they had a plug-in
architecture like for things like Adobe
Flash that was much more robust against
stability issues and they had a very
fast JavaScript engine. Firefox also had
a fast JavaScript engine and we you know
traded back and forth uh you know taking
the performance crown but they had some
real structural advantages and at the
same time Mozilla made a big and
ambitious bet in the early 2010s to try
to build a mobile phone operating system
uh because there was this sense that
mobile is coming and both Android and
iOS are potentially hostile platforms
that are not going to allow Firefox to
do what it did on desktop on their
platforms.
And the belief was that the only
possibility was to create a new mobile
operating system uh that was based on
web technology. And you know there was
something to that idea and there was
quite a lot of interest from the
industry a very surprising amount of
interest and we had a lot of partners
but ultimately it didn't work and the
big bet that Mozilla made on Firefox OS
created a lot of resource competition
with the work that needed to happen to
keep Firefox competitive exactly at the
time when it was needed the most. And so
Firefox really had a lot of um gaps with
respect to Chrome. I think the
multipprocess architecture was a big
one. The stability issues particularly
coming from Adobe Flash which was widely
used particularly for streaming video
which was becoming a thing. That was
another big gap. And Firefox also had
some legacy baggage around its uh
browser extension API where the way that
you would make a browser extension I
mean the whole concept of browser
extension really arose from the Firefox
architecture where you could just inject
anything anywhere and the Firefox
application was written in JavaScript
and markup and you could just modify it
with an extension by just adding more
JavaScript and more markup and more CSS.
And this was really cool and that's
where people first got the notion that
you could configure and change your
browser um and extend it with new
functionality. But the problem was that
there were no well- definfined
interfaces. And so all of these
extensions were depending on all of
these internal details of how the
browser worked. And anytime we change
anything we would break an extension and
so that was a very real and significant
drag with respect to trying to
architecturally modernize the browser.
You mentioned prior to Google's funding,
this was a group of a bunch of people
that were working for free in many
cases. I kind of curious because I
haven't done a lot of open source stuff.
What is the incentive structure? Why why
would people spend so much time working
for free on a project like this?
So I think it probably varies but the
world was quite different back then and
open source there were not first of all
a lot of opportunities for people to
contribute to something major and
meaningful right like these days much of
the software stack that everybody uses
many projects are open source but there
were not so many of those back at the
time and so I think that it was an
interesting opportunity to have impact
and I think for a lot of people like I
mentioned Boris he literally got
involved in Mozilla because he had no
way to browse the internet in his dorm
room. One option was he was like at MIT
at the time I think and you know he
could either VNC into some like Solaris
thing with Internet Explorer 5 or he
could use this build of Netscape that he
downloaded that was just constantly
crashing. And so he he got involved just
because he wanted to fix something for
himself and he had this vision of how he
wanted it to be better for him. And then
he realized that there were so many
other people out there that were also
looking for the same things and trying
to fix this stuff. And once you dive
into a codebase like this, it is just an
amazing intellectual challenge because
the codebase was just so vast and so
complicated. And so he was like a math
major, right? But this was in some ways
like even harder. And I think that that
um challenge was another major aspect.
But I think the biggest aspect was the
motivation of the Mozilla mission and
what we were trying to achieve because
the I think a lot of principles that
people take for granted about you know
how the web should work that it should
be open and it should be interoperable
that it shouldn't be controlled by one
company and even that that about the
internet itself right you know the
Mozilla mission is about making sure
that the internet is a global public
resource that is open and accessible to
all and I think if you grew up in the
90s when Microsoft oft was eating the
world. That was not a given. That was
not the dominant way of thinking about
how technology platforms should work.
And Mozilla had a vision of how it could
be different. And it had a means of
executing that vision, right? It wasn't
just an advocacy organization arguing
that tech companies should do something
different. It was actually going out and
doing something and succeeding and
creating a browser that gave users
choice to block popups and control over
their experience and the ability to
block ads and the ability to have tab
browsing and all these things that they
weren't getting before and creating that
reality and making the world better in
that way I think was very inspiring to a
lot of people.
>> Yeah. I'm kind of curious like you know
once you got there I want to hear a
little bit about the projects that
you're working on and the various
stories of things that happened in the
early days. Are there any projects that
you felt were particularly interesting
or contributed to your career?
>> Yeah, so I got started working on all
sorts of things like I think as an
intern that I worked on was the uh front
end for the new mobile browser but this
was before there was Android and iOS. So
it was actually for like Nokia Mimo uh
and that's what I started on. Then I
started working on the graphics engine.
I worked on the image rendering library.
And there was very much a sense back
then just because there was so much code
that you know was largely unowned that
as soon as you show up and you start
working on something and you like fix
one thing, you start looking around
you're like hey who who owns this? And
they're like you do now. And so I really
I ended my first internship owning like
quite a lot of code in the Firefox
browser. And that felt to me like a
really big and important responsibility
to make sure that um you know this stuff
went well. I think I was particularly
motivated to work on the really like the
hardest and gnarliest parts of the code.
um the parts that felt most critical
when you know after Chrome came out and
then Firefox was coming back with its
first counterattack of trying to build a
browser that was more performance
competitive right particularly around
JavaScript. So Chrome launched with this
JavaScript engine called V8 that was you
know had a just in time compiler and it
was very fast and we were intending to
ship our own just in time compiler uh
for our JavaScript engine but there was
a lot of challenge at the end of
actually getting this thing shipped
particularly around this very
complicated area of how the JavaScript
engine talks to the rest of the system
you know how the the bindings between
the JavaScript and the DOM which were
referred to as XP connect and so
literally There were months of delay of
getting Firefox 4 out the door because
of all of the tangled web of that
architecture and I, you know, also at
the advice of Damon at the time decided
to dive in and try to help make that
stuff better. And so I ended up working
on that code and the thing about that
code was that it was very
uh tied up in a lot of security
considerations in the browser. When the
browsers and the web were first
designed, you know, JavaScript was
famously designed in 10 days, people did
not fully think through all of the
security implications of this
architecture. Uh, both in terms of the
web platform and the browser itself. So,
Firefox as a browser, one of the cool
things about it was that all of the
application on the front end was also
written in markup and JavaScript. But
all of that relied from a security
perspective on making sure that a
website would be properly isolated from
touching other websites and from
touching the browser replication itself.
And this was all a very complicated mess
of security enforcement in this
DOMbinding code. And it was not perfect.
And there was this cat-and- mouse game
between people working on Firefox and
this external community of security
researchers who were constantly finding
new ways to poke holes in this, right?
And you do some very very clever thing
with, you know, function.bind and you
end up slithering up the prototype chain
and suddenly you're like in the address
bar and tab code. And once you do that,
you know, the browser and perhaps the
computer are compromised. And so there
was um there were a number of
researchers, there was one, I think
their name was Mozbug RA4. We never
learned what their actual name was. Uh
rumor had it that they worked in they
lived in a country where security
research was illegal. But there was very
much like a weekly back and forth
between uh people at Mozilla working on
Firefox and Mozbar 4 of new um potential
paths of vulnerability. So Firefox 4
definitely I think introduced a much
more robust architecture and that was
when I got involved with some of this
stuff. But there started to be other and
additional security researchers who
showed up who were finding new ways to
poke holes in it. And what really
started to worry me was that there were
certain categories of things that we
didn't really have a way to fix in a
robust manner. You know, we could put a
band-aid over that particular part. We
could wallpaper it over, but there were
usually ways that you could apply the
same attack in another part of the
codebase. And
I started to get pretty worried about
this. And I launched a very large cross
functional effort that I spent, you
know, at least over a year on which I
referred to as slaughterhouse. Um, and
that was because, you know, it was a
joke because there were these things
called Chrome object wrappers that we
needed to get rid of. Um, but there was
generally a sense um that this could be
a really big problem if this these types
of exploits were to be weaponized in the
wild uh before we did something about
it. And there was one particular
researcher who I worked with quite a bit
um who was really good at identifying
and finding these issues. And so what
would happen was be these external
researchers. They would send us
something. They would file it in a
confidential bug in Bugzilla and our bug
tracker. And then we would look at it
and be like, "Yep, this is a real
issue." And then we had a bounty
program, right, where we would pay them
a small amount of money um as as a thank
you and an incentive to uh bring it to
us and, you know, not sell it on the
black market. But the black market
certainly paid more and sometimes there
would be zero day exploits where you'd
have to sort of jump on some new thing
and fix it and ship uh a fix within you
know 24 hours to make sure that users
were protected. And sometimes
these attacks got ahead of us. And so
there was one situation where
uh somebody flagged me that there was a
zero day exploit in the wild um that had
been discovered. I think it was on like
Moscow Times.com and I was disassembling
it and then I had this realization that
like I knew who had written this exploit
um because it was one of the security
researchers that we work with and
without thinking too hard I fired off an
email to this guy being like hey like
you're you're double crossing us right
like you're not supposed to sell these
things if you report them to us and he
got back to me and the thing about
security researchers is that they're
extremely paranoid he's like no no no I
didn't this must mean that my devices
must be compromised at a very deep
level. And the only thing I can think to
do here is to go off the grid. And
we then discovered a basically like an
hour later that actually it was Mozilla
that had been compromised that Bugzilla,
our bug tracker, had been compromised by
a thread actor. And I tried to write
back to the researcher, but at that
point he'd already gone offline and we
couldn't reach him. And so it was
several weeks later that we got a phone
call from a bowling alley in upstate New
York where this researcher had gone into
hiding and was trying to, you know,
throw off the people that were after
him. And we managed to explain that
actually, sorry, this was our bad and
had to help him get back on his feet.
But it was a really big problem that
Bugzilla had been compromised because
that is where you have the records of
all of the interesting security attacks
that people have discovered against the
browser. But the amazing thing was that
Slaughterhouse had just wrapped up and
that out of I think 45 of the I don't
know something on the order of 45 of the
bugs that the thread actor had um
excfiltrated, we had fixed all but two
of them. And with this sort of new
architecture that basically fixed it.
And so that really impressed upon me the
importance of getting ahead of things on
security and making sure that you have
the right architecture because sometimes
you find you're in a self a situation
where you don't have the luxury of the
time to fix it.
>> How'd you know that that security
researcher wrote that vulnerability?
>> People have very particular styles and
in this particular area of security or
of exploits which is which is different
than other kinds. Um, there was just a
lot of people's fingerprints on it,
right? You could tell because these were
things that were handwritten logic
attacks where you were using very
particular parts of like I'm going to
take this API and then I'm going to bind
this function to it and then I'm going
to send this call like around async
through the event loop twice and then
I'm going to do this, right? Like there
was a very particular way and these were
all handwritten. There is a different
type of security attack that was also a
major issue at the time which were
memory safety vulnerabilities and these
were much less of a artisal thing and
more things that you would produce by
tools particularly by fuzzing tools. And
so this was also a major issue that um
Mozilla was grappling with because he
would have people who would run these
fuzzers against the codebase and the
codebase was written in C++ and there
are lots of ways to have memory hazards
in C++ and really any one of them is the
sort of like web page takes over your
computer situation and so we were really
struggling to find ways to deal with
that in a robust manner. Um, and that
was really one of the things that
motivated Mozilla's investment in Rust.
>> So I could see and I'm just trying to
understand here the the security issue
here is there's some front-end code that
abuses or does some special path in
Firefox and then can take over Firefox
in that case in the past. But how does
it take over the computer? Wouldn't the
operating system kind of shield um
ideally from Firefox doing crazy stuff?
>> So certainly not at the time like
originally particularly on Windows
applications largely ran with system
privileges and if you took over the you
know the the classic thing that security
researchers would do to prove that
they'd pawned your machine was to launch
the calculator um like the Windows
calculator right and so you'd run this
exploit you really have to trust the
person who sent it to you that it wasn't
going to do anything bad but you know
calc.exe exe that was that was the
proof. As time went on and you know
Chrome had a major hand in improving the
table stakes of how browsers worked,
there were additional layers of
protection that were put on, right? And
so some of these include inprocess
sandboxing um as well as operating
system level sandboxing. And so the
architecture that browsers like Firefox
and Chrome have today involves a very
you know defense in-depth multiple level
of uh multiple levels of protection
including operating system level
sandboxing that is applied um to things
like you know the the rendering and
content processes.
That said, this was all bolted on over
time on Windows. And Windows, unlike an,
you know, a platform like iOS. Um, iOS
is designed from the beginning with an
an with an application sandboxing model
where applications are just applications
and they have their own little world.
That was not how Windows worked. And so
evolving Windows and evolving the
security critical applications that sit
on top of Windows like browsers to deal
with these sorts of attacks is honestly
an ongoing challenge. Did you ever
figure out how a Bugzilla was
compromised?
>> I I think it was a credential leak from
an employee like that. I I'm 85% sure
that that's what it was. And that was I
think before we had things like
two-factor authentication um for logging
into Bugzilla. You know, Bugzilla was a
very old tool that dated back into the
90s. And so similarly, it was something
that had to evolve with the threats over
time.
>> One thing that I was curious about is as
an organization,
how do you prioritize security? Because
for instance at the time there was also
these big investments in performance and
I'm sure there was a bunch of other
things
>> for sure. Yeah. Security is one of those
long-term things that is very easy to
take a short-term perspective on and
ignore and that is perhaps a decision
that some products will make uh given
where they are but it's not something
that you can do as a long-term browser.
And so honestly from my perspective it's
a cultural thing at Mozilla that from
the very beginning back before there was
any sort of management structure and
performance measurement and you know
company objectives it was just
understood that we had an obligation to
protect our users and to keep them safe
and I think that persists
that means that there's a lot of I would
say ongoing bottomup energy towards
making sure that we improve security And
there's a lot of pride that people at
Mosilla take in the security of Firefox.
Um because Firefox does not have you
know I think that the Chrome security
org you know on its own is like on the
order of you know 70 plus people and we
don't have anything close to that but it
is considered to be a shared
responsibility and we have a lot of
people who are very dedicated to that
and trying to think ahead right like
slaughterhouse the project that I led
that was not any kind of top- down edict
of we need to go fix this it was that I
was responsible for the code and I felt
that this was important that we needed
to get it right And one of the things
that I'm very proud of at Mozilla today
is that um there are there's an annual
security um competition called Pone to
Own where researchers show up and
test their exploits and receive prizes
for compromising the browsers. And
generally speaking, they always find a
way to compromise every browser, right?
Like no browser is perfectly secure. And
Firefox for the last two years has won
the award of being fastest to patch um
within you know on the order of 24
hours. And this is only possible because
we have people literally in time zones
around the world uh who are just working
non-stop to get it out. Um and it's not
something that we ask people to do. It's
there's no management edict that
somebody needs to stay up late or work
on a weekend to do it. People are just
motivated to do it because they care.
You mentioned no performance reviews and
this uh scrappy bottoms up culture. How
does that kind of culture work?
>> I think in the world of prior to being
much management, it was just uneven. I
think as you would as you would guess,
right? And I think that it was generally
things worked well because the caliber
and dedication was very high, but it was
very much a bottoms up culture, right?
And if there was somebody who was owning
that particular part of the code that
wasn't doing a good job, everybody just
kind of lived with that. And um there
also I would say there was very much a
notion of people having ownership of
areas and that being um somewhat final,
right? Mozilla had a governance
structure that was very much insulated
against any sort of executive power. uh
it was this module system and people
were owners of the modules and uh even
the initial access control system I
think was called desperate um and it was
very much a notion of distributed and
decentralized decision-m
I think that that culture was very
powerful and there are still elements of
that culture that I think are important
to preserve today but there are also
ways in which it fell short and needed
to change and one of the things that I
have spent a lot of thought on over you
know recent years is finding myself in a
leadership position is how do we
preserve those aspects of the technical
culture that make it great while also
addressing some of the shortcomings.
>> You mentioned a little bit about C++ and
memory safety issues. That's a very
classic thing and I know that Rust was
developed at Mozilla to tackle those
problems in large part. So I'm curious
um can you tell me a little bit about
the adoption of Rust and you know how it
solves the problem?
>> Right.
>> So in the early 2010s it was pretty
clear that Mozilla and Firefox the code
had some real structural issues and a
lot of these were issues that we could
address through sheer hard work. Right?
This included building a multipprocess
architecture um and evolving our
extension architecture such that stuff
you know didn't have its tendrils into
all the undocumented interfaces within
the browser um and building uh native
video playback so that we didn't have to
rely on Adobe Flash anymore. Like these
were all large but incremental projects
to address specific architectural
issues. But there were two architectural
issues that were very difficult to
address in that way. And the first one I
already mentioned is memory safety,
right? Because when you have a codebase
that's written in C++,
a large portion of the defects that you
can make are the sort of defects that
compromise the browser and without sac
and in the absence of sandboxing
compromise the computer. Um, and that
was just a very difficult thing to deal
with uh in a non-whackole fashion.
And there's another piece which was that
particularly at the time there was a
increase in the number of cores that
were shipping on devices. But browsers
were still largely
singlethreaded. And this meant that you
were leaving a lot of the available
performance on the table if you didn't
have multi-threaded code. But if you did
have multi-threaded code, especially in
C++, you just had all sorts of very
difficult nondeterministic bugs that
were very difficult to track down. And
some of these also became memory safety
issues that became exploitable defects.
And there was this notion that both of
these were rooted in deficiencies of the
C++ programming language. And all
browsers are written in C++. But you
know in 2010 Firefox had just taken on
the world and opened up the web and
there was a sense that we could do the
impossible. And so we began an effort um
you know sponsoring some research that
uh some people internally had around
building a new programming language and
this programming language was Rust and
the idea of Rust eventually became that
we would have a programming language
that had static guarantees at compile
time that number one you didn't have
memory safety issues and number two that
you didn't have race conditions. And
this idea was that first we would build
a new programming language with these
properties which was difficult to do.
And then we would use this programming
language to build a new browser engine
for Firefox. And so the Rust project
co-evolved with this project called
servo which was
a ongoing evolving test bed for the rest
programming language with the intention
of building a browser that was memory
safe but more importantly was parallel
because there was a sense that we could
solve these architectural issues and
close the gap with Chrome but that also
we needed something to leaprog Chrome
and there was a belief that concurrency
and safe concurrency powered by a new
programming language was the way to do
that.
>> Yeah. I want to talk about the
competition with Chrome at the time
because you said they launched with a uh
more performant browser and also they
were hammering you guys with uh
distribution advantages. I'm curious
what was the strategy at that time from
the Mozilla team to compete with Chrome.
So the strategy to compete with Chrome
was
multifaceted.
One of the parts was a recognition. I
think there was a little bit of denial
in the very early days about the deep
value that some of Chrome's
architectural advantages would provide.
And this was, you know, they came out
with a JavaScript engine with what's
referred to as a method JIT. We had a
tracing JIT. We thought the tracing jit
was good and was going to be better, but
in the end it wasn't. Chrome came out
with multipprocess architecture. I
remember the first thing that I heard
was, "Yeah, good luck doing that on
Mac." And then they figured out how to
do it on Mac. And there was a belief
that some of these things were not
possible until they were. And then once
they were, that they weren't the most
important thing. But eventually it
became clear that uh things like a
multipprocess architecture and things
like native video playback were really
essential and we had this issue
particularly on video playback where
because Chrome first had a better
plug-in architecture uh for Adobe Flash
and then was also early to introduce
native video playback they were able to
have a much more stable experience on
YouTube which was blowing up at the
time. Whereas Firefox on YouTube, which
was what everybody wanted to do on the
internet, was just crashing left and
right. And it wasn't stuff that we could
fix, it was Adobe's fault, and we really
couldn't do anything about it. And so we
had to work on
a lot of these really hard but discreet
challenges um of closing the gap with
Chrome. But then at the same time, there
was a desire of you can't just close the
gap. have to do something new and you
have to do something that is better and
rust and servo were our strategy for
doing better.
>> So you mentioned the strategy with servo
and the rewrite and rust. How did it go?
Was it successful? Well, we we know that
Google's distribution eventually
dominated, but how did the efforts with
servo go?
So on the one hand, servo and rust had
against all odds captured something
really real and servo as a browser
engine prototype had a lot of really
amazing stuff in it, right? It was not
complete, but it did have the skeleton
of certain features that had never been
done before, including a multi-threaded
CSS engine. But the problem was that we
had a team of you know a dozen people
working on rust and servo. Google had
hundreds and hundreds and hundreds of
engineers who were working on chromium.
We had less than that but still most of
Mozilla's efforts were directed towards
Gecko and Firefox because that was the
product that we had in market. So we had
this situation where in order to build a
competitive browser engine, it's not
like you need to just do this one time.
It's the accumulation of all of the work
over all of these years of hundreds of
engineers working on improving it and
improving the architecture, improving
the performance, improving the features.
And so every year there was more and
more stuff that server would have to
catch up with. And I think if you just
look at it, there's it's was very
difficult to believe that we would ever
end up in a situation where servo would
be competitive with a regular um
production browser engine. And so circa
like 2014 2015 that was a situation
where there was really a sense that we
needed to deliver a fully refreshed
version of Firefox that really got us
back in the game. that included this
parallel CSS engine that we uplifted
from servo and this was a project that I
personally led and was really the
highlight of my career working on it
because it was so exciting to be doing
something really new in a new
programming language that and every step
of the way there was this notion that
like that's definitely never going to
work right like how are you even going
to like hook this thing up and then we
hooked it up and we had it traversing
the DOM over C++ plus um you know we
have a C++ DOM and we're having this
Rust CSS engine and how you get these
two things to work together. There was
no tooling for it. We had to build it
all ourselves. At the end of the day it
was really a dramatic performance
improvement. I think it improved like
rendering time on Amazon.com by on the
order of 25%. which is just enormous in
terms of um web performance. And because
it was parallel and it can run on all of
your cores, it was and still is the
fastest CSS engine in the market.
Firefox really got back in the game and
was really performance competitive with
everything else out there. And that was
a really exciting moment for everybody
and realizing that if we just coordinate
and we do all the technical effort and
we make the right bets, we can win.
>> Okay. Okay. So, you mentioned that this
was one of the most proud moments of
your career and like a major launch,
very exciting project. I'm kind of
curious to talk about the career parts
of it. So, where were you in your career
at this point? And maybe you can talk
about how it grew um as you worked on
these projects.
>> Sure. So, I think when I started, I
don't know if Mozilla had levels. Um I
certainly wasn't aware of them if they
existed. Uh it was a culture of choose
your own title. Uh the title that I
chose for myself was negative entropy.
Uh that was sort of what I wanted to do
on this incredibly complex and gnarly
codebase. As a fun fact, my favorite
intern uh made his title entropy. Um but
we were really on the same side. Uh I
think by the time we were shipping
Firefox Quantum, Mozilla had developed I
would say a more industry standard um uh
career progression. And so, you know,
you had you come in as, you know, just
title of engineer and then you've got
senior staff, senior staff. At the time
when I was working on quantum CSS, uh I
believe I was um my I had reached the
level of senior staff and upon the
successful launch of Firefox Quantum, I
and the engineer who led the other half
of Quantum Quantum Flow uh were promoted
to the level of principal engineer. Um
and at the time that was there were not
very many principal engineers, you know,
like probably fewer than five. Um, and
so that was um, a pretty significant
jump, but my long-term
dream was to be like Boris Sabarski. And
Boris Sabarski was one of Mozilla's
three distinguished engineers. And so
that was really what I had my sights on
in terms of the level of impact that I
wanted to have. And the way that I
really aimed at having this impact was
by trying to contribute to as many parts
of the code as possible and just be
prolific. And so after um working on
quantum CSS, I went and worked on web
render and I worked on mobile and
multipprocess and layout and all sorts
of different parts of the
uh of the code. And I remember my
manager at the time, Joe Hilderbrand,
who ran engineering, told me that he
wanted me to spend one day a week when I
didn't open my terminal. And I was just
shocked. I was like, what? What are you
what are you asking me to do here,
right? You're asking me to not work for
an entire day. And he was encouraging me
to start thinking about it in the impact
that I could have in a much broader way
as opposed to direct contributions to
the code. And so this was something that
I started to think about, but it was
really not the natural way that I
thought to work.
>> When you talk about the individual
contributions, because you mentioned
that was your way of having a lot of
impact. Do you have a way of thinking
about which contributions are more
impactful than others?
>> I was very much motivated to work on
whatever felt like the biggest problem.
And so that was early on that felt like
the DOM bindings and XP connect and all
the security stuff. And then at some
point it was the media playback to solve
the YouTube problem. And then it was
multipprocess. And then it was this uh
rest and servo CSS stuff. And after that
I thought that web render which was the
new graphics back end that we were
uplifting from uh servo. So I went and
worked on that. Then mobile. So I was
always drawn, I think, to what felt like
the most pressing problem. And my model
of how to have impact on that was to
jump in and learn all of the code in the
most pressing problem and help work on
it. And not just necessarily typing all
of the code myself, but working with the
other leaders in those areas on figuring
out what the right things to do would be
and reviewing code and setting direction
and setting priorities. So there were
aspects of leadership, but it was all
very much oriented around the code that
needed the most help.
>> So you were prolific, but it was a
guided search specifically on the
biggest problems for the organization.
>> That was how I thought about it. Yes.
>> One thing that I'm curious about because
in the industry when it comes to career
growth, I often hear two methodologies.
One is where people they focus on the
promo first and foremost. And as a
byproduct to get the promo they you know
grow in level or skills and various
other things behaviors and in the other
school of thought it's ignore the promos
but focus on the behaviors focus on the
skills and then the promos will come.
I'm curious your thought between the two
methodologies and which one you think is
better for structuring an engineering
career.
>> I have pretty strong opinions about
this. I am very much of the mind that it
is important to focus on impact and not
the title and I think there are a number
of reasons for this but that is
certainly what I look for now that I'm
in a situation when I am helping people
with their careers and I am often in the
decision of you know figuring out you
know who's the right person to advance
and what I am looking for is I am
looking for the impact And my general
philosophy is that if you are having
that level of impact, you don't need to
sell yourself in that way. Um or sell
yourself is not quite the right word,
but there is a particular philosophy
where you want to promo hack, right? You
want to pin your management chain down
on what are the things that I need to do
to receive this promotion. And
that just speaking frankly is very
annoying, right? Um there are aspects to
this that I think are just intuitive to
how I at least as a person perceive
things. You know like I'm a father of
kids and when my daughter asks me like
when you know I ask her to do something
and she's like uh you know will you give
me this if I do that right it's it just
does not um land well with me. But I
think that there's also a substantive
aspect to it which is that if you are
really focused on the impact that is how
you are really going to achieve things
right whereas if you're focused on
checking some boxes that somebody has
presented to you then you're in this
awkward situation where it's like well I
did technically say that if you did this
you know that would maybe make a case
for this next level but the way in which
you did it and was very sort of focused
on checking the box as opposed to having
the impact and at the end of the day
impact is what matters and impact which
is what needs to be recognized and
rewarded.
>> One thing that I hear often because I
think this is a failure mode for
engineers that are a little more
softspoken is they're great at writing
code and landing it and having impact,
but they're a little weaker on the, you
know, selling yourself or kind of
marketing your work. And so that kind of
bites people. So sometimes I hear career
advice that is focused on, you know,
hey, make sure you create a brag
document and you share the wins when you
land the thing. And and I think a lot of
those people don't have an ulterior
motive of let me, you know, kind of
connive my way into the promo. Um, but I
think there is this this real thing of
promos are decided by people and there's
some value in I guess a balance because
obviously if you were completely
conniving you say hey I'm going to talk
to my manager and sell my work to him.
That's kind of not ideal. But you know
making posts or sharing it and thinking
about the levels and stuff seems to be a
good way for those um little quieter or
less proactive engineers and structuring
their career. So you know how would you
kind of balance those two frames of
thinking? I think there are often
multiple ways to frame similar
activities,
but that the framing of how you think
about it is going to have a big impact
on how you carry it out and therefore
what it actually achieves. And so I
think a good example of this is this
notion of that you brought up selling
yourself or brag documents or something
like that.
I think it is important that people have
visibility and visibility around the
work that they're doing. And this is
just a very like a basic fact about
impact because if you want to have
impact, you need to be connected to
people who understand what are the
biggest challenges and you need to be
coordinated and you also need to make
sure that people understand what you are
capable of such that they can put you in
a position of having more impact. But if
you think of it as I am trying to brag
more about me versus I am trying to
communicate and coordinate and create
visibility for work that I think that is
important. You will have very different
outcomes.
>> Yeah, it's it's interesting because it's
it's subtle. I feel like you could have
two people with different incentive. One
goes into it saying, "I'm going to
create this update so I get visibility
and the other person comes in to say,
I'm going to create this update so the
right people know the right things." And
they get to the same path at the end of
the day, but it's like this subtle, it's
worded slightly differently and people
can tell. A lot of it is the degree to
which you know how much you make it
about you versus how much you make it
about other people and the work and the
team. And everybody knows you know that
the person sending the update likely had
a significant hand in the work. And a
very important thing to do as part of
those updates is to make sure that you
give um visibility to other people and
to thank the team and not make it so
much about you. Uh because also that is
a way to work well with people. Um to
have people feel like you are a you know
humble leader and somebody that they
want to work with and that is an
important part of leadership is making
sure that you create recognition for
other people's contributions um and
don't make it all about you. It is an
ideal world that people have impact and
they get recognized exactly as much as
their impact. One thing that I can
imagine happening though is you know
there's that idiom that the squeaky
wheel gets the grease. Basically, if you
had a loud person that is really vying
for their promo and you know making all
aggressively trying to make the posts
and you know constantly bothering their
manager, hey, I want to get promoted
that oftent times assuming they have
impact. If they don't have impact then
it's not going to nothing's going to
happen. But assuming if they're also a
high performer and they're doing that
compared to the high performer that's
you know reasonable, quiet and solid,
not selfish that actually that loud
person unfortunately I think in most
organizations will get rewarded first or
faster. What do you think about that?
>> I think it does depend on the
organization and it depends on the
technical culture. Um, you know, one of
the things that we try really hard to do
in our our culture is to not reward
that. But I think there is a balance to
be struck because my message is not
don't be ambitious, but rather think
about your ambition in terms of the
impact that you want to have as opposed
to the status you want to achieve. And
if you have the impact and create
visibility around the impact, the rest
will follow. And yes, there are edge
cases and there are probably some
situations where um people lobbying for
themselves will kind of grudgingly get
themselves a little more consideration
just because it's top of mind. But the
best kinds of conversations that I like
to have with people are not
conversations where people come and ask
how do I get promoted? It is how do I
grow my career and have more impact?
Right? Like am I working on the most
important thing? Like what could I do to
grow? What could I do to have more
impact? Right? And I think that those
are important conversations to have with
your um leadership to uh make sure that
you're focused on the right things
because the worst and saddest thing is
when somebody is just working so hard at
something that is just not that
important and not going to have the type
of impact that they ultimately want to
do. And they might do a great job at it,
but it's just not the right thing. And
so I do think that some coordination of
like this is the type of impact that I
want to have and not everybody wants to
have that kind of impact and making it
known that you want to have that impact
and you're looking for swings at the bat
and you're looking for opportunities to
do more. I think that that is helpful.
But trying to pin people down of like
what are the boxes that I can check and
you know I did this like are you good to
promote me now is just honestly
extremely annoying from my perspective.
Uh, and I just think zooming out at a
level of life, you don't want the people
in leadership to find you to be
annoying.
>> So, in your case, you were focusing on
impact. You had these role models of
these dees that you wanted to be like,
and I'm kind of curious, what eventually
did the growth look like? And how did
your impact grow?
I was really focused on continuing to
work on like what was the hardest and
gnarliest challenge in the browser and
moving on from team to team. And that
was really the model that I had in my
head. And I did have in my head this
idea that I eventually, you know, wanted
to have the level of impact that Boris
had. And I assumed that that would
eventually mean um becoming a
distinguished engineer. And then at some
point um the CTO at the time, Eric
Rcora,
sat me down because at this point, you
know, Boris and David and this guy,
Robert O' Callahan, had been
distinguished engineers kind of since
the beginning, you know, since maybe
like 2010 or something. And we hadn't
made any new ones since. And the CTO sat
me down and he said, "Look, I want to
let you know that for the first time in,
you know, almost a decade, we're going
to make some new distinguished
engineers. And I thought you should know
that you're not going to be one of
them." And this was, I think, a little
bit surprising to me because I do think
that, you know, I thought and that I
think anybody at the time would say that
at that time, like probably maybe not
quite Boris level, but that in terms of
knowledge of all of the Firefox code,
that was something that I had more than
almost anyone else. But what he
explained to me was that that was a more
traditional model of distinguished
engineer inside of Mozilla, but that he
was looking for something different now
and that he was looking for something
that was more oriented around industry
impact
and that was very much how he saw the
world.
>> The definition of impact seems to have
shifted while you were thinking about
your DE journey. Did you ever debate the
definition of impact or what was your
thinking when you saw that the criteria
was updated?
>> Honestly, it was just kind of inspiring
for me. I think there was, you know,
some people were concerned that I would
be upset, but I think it was more like,
you know, you work out and you think
that you're really strong and you know,
go do some Pilates move or something.
You're like, "Oh my gosh, like this
muscle that I have, I didn't even know
that I have, but it is extremely weak."
Um, and the truth is is that there are
lots of different ways to define DE and
it's what matters for an organization,
right? The thing that mattered early on
in Mozilla and what was the make or
break for Firefox success was just the
management of this incredibly complex
and sprawling codebase by very few
people and the thing that was needed
most was a kind of prolific contributor
and enabler of that and that was the
archetype of distinguished engineer at
Mozilla. There are other companies where
distinguish engineer means something
else. Right? I know that some companies
generally it means you built a billion
dollar business. But that is not what
Mozilla is about. And what Mozilla is
about is changing the world. And so the
criteria for DE are really focused
around that. And this was I think an
inspiring thing for me. And I still
think that I, you know, didn't
ultimately, you know, I still probably
have not had the level of industry
impact of some of our other
distinguished engineers. Um, and so
probably in the end when I got to DE, it
was maybe a combination or a hybrid of
the old and the new definitions. Um but
understanding that model of thinking
about the world and that model of impact
I think was very profound for me and
really oriented how um I directed my
efforts.
>> I'd love to hear some examples of what a
DE level of impact looks like. Can you
talk about some of the people who have
done really impressive engineering work?
>> Sure. Yeah. So um at the time there were
you know when we had this conversation
there were three new uh distinguished
engineers that were promoted. So the
first one uh was Martin Thompson and
Martin still is at Mosilla today and
Martin is an international standards
extraordinaire in terms of the
development of the technical standards
that power the internet and so his name
is you know in the author line of
protocols like HTTP2 and quick and um
web push and
he was heavily involved in the creation
of WebRTC and geoloccation. He authored
other protocols like Oblivious HTTP.
Like I don't know I honestly not super
familiar but it wouldn't surprise me if
there's really nobody else who has had
that level of prolific impact on all of
the core technical standards of the
internet. And this isn't just about, you
know, doing some editorial work on
making sure that all of the drafts are
formatted correctly. This is about core
design challenges of making these
protocols better in a way that advances
Mozilla's objectives. And so similar to
the situation around TLS, there were
generally problems around the privacy
and security and performance of the
legacy HTTP protocols. And by designing
new ones that made it faster while at
the same time making it more private and
having less metadata leaked and having
fewer security issues meant that there
was a business incentive for the entire
industry to move onto these protocols
because they were faster. and by
designing them that way he managed to
really increase the privacy and security
of the internet. So that was one
archetype.
The second was Luke Wagner. Luke was
many pe Luke was probably if there was
anyone in the world the most
single-handedly responsible for the
development of web assembly.
So historically, people wanted to run
code in browsers that was not written in
JavaScript.
Maybe you wanted to run AutoCAD and they
didn't want to rewrite the entire
codebase in JS. And the original way of
doing that was through plugins where
there was this basically native binary
blob that got shunted into the browser
window. And it was awful. Had lots of
terrible security properties and bad
user experience. And so we tried to move
away from that. And the first idea was
actually from there was an engineer who
worked on it as a side project alone
skai who made this tool at Mozilla
called inscriptton. And the idea of
scripton was we just take the C++ and
then we compile it to some very naive uh
JavaScript and then run the JavaScript
which technically worked but it was
extremely slow. And Luke was one of the
lead engineers of the spider monkey
JavaScript engine in Firefox at the time
and he wanted to make this something
that was actually viable. So the first
thing they did was there was some back
and forth of well how do we optimize the
JavaScript engine for what uh mcripton
is emitting and that was obviously not a
sustainable approach. But then they had
this idea of asomjs. And the idea was
that mscripton would output a subset of
JS which would be detected by the
JavaScript engine. And the JS engine
would then verify that it was from this
restricted subset which was sort of a
proto byte code format and then run it
in a more natively unoptimized way. But
and and so this was what got the
flywheel going of people actually being
able to say, "Hey, we can deploy these
amazing native experiences that are
compiled and that they're running in the
browser because the ultimate goal was
that we wanted basically everything on
the desktop to be running in the browser
or most things on the desktop to be
running in the browser." And there was
some stuff that just couldn't. And that
flywheel then created enough industry
momentum to say why don't we actually
create a new by code format which was
web assembly where you could have code
that was native but that was also
sandboxed and portable and running
inside the browser. And this was at a
time when Google was pushing a very
different technology that was more akin
to plugins. They had this thing called
native client or knackle and then they
had this thing called pinnacle. And
there were a lot of very complicated
industry dynamics of getting all of the
browsers to get on board with this web
assembly train. And so Luke managed the
technical pieces and the political
pieces to eventually forge a browser
consensus on web assembly which has been
a very transformative technology in
terms of what browsers can do and even
what can be done outside of browsers
because web assembly was built with such
great technical properties is now being
used all over the place on the back end.
Um things like serverless. So uh this is
a bunch of the work that the bite code
alliance is involved in. So that is
another archetype of impact of the
creation of web assembly. The third
distinguished engineer at the time was
Tim Terbury who was our codec lead. And
so one major problem that Mozilla and
honestly the web had back in the early
days was that all of the video playback
happened through proprietary plugins
like Adobe Flash. And
you would think that the obvious answer,
which is the obvious answer, is to build
native video playback into the browser.
But the problem was that the formats
that are used to compress video are
heavily patent- encumbered. And there
are lots of reasons for this, but it's
just the way the world works where in
this particular space, everybody is
fighting over patents. And this meant
that an open- source browser like
Mozilla Firefox couldn't ship native
support for the H.264 264
uh codec which was really what was
powering most of the video on the
internet at the time. It was the most
efficient codec and that was what
YouTube was using. And this was a pretty
significant problem for us. And so
Mozilla worked over a number of years to
develop truly open and free and
non-patent enencumbered and royalty-free
codecs. And
the team led by Tim first developed an
audio codec called Opus and then they
worked to develop a video codec called
Dala. And Dala was then incorporated
into AV1 which became an industry
standard
uh video format that is now developed by
the alliance for open media which is a
consortium across many companies like
Mozilla and Google and Apple and
Netflix. And so this is basically what
powers video today. And a lot of that
vision around what would it mean to
actually develop truly patent encumbered
video codecs came from tip. So those I
think are three archetypes of the types
of worldchanging impact that you can
have as an engineering IC at a place
like Mozilla.
>> Yeah. The the achievement of these
engineers is absurd. I mean you
mentioned web assembly. I mean, I think
of a business like Figma as possible
because of a lot of that work. Um, and
that's a tens of billions of dollars
industry or I mean company just by its
public market cap. And so it the the
value that's being created by these
distinguished is absurd. What's
interesting to me is, I guess, because
it's a more open-source company, the
value capture is very different. I'm
curious, is that something that I don't
know, people in at Mozilla are ever not
feeling great about because they've
created so much value, but the capture
is happening by these capitalist uh
other companies.
>> Yeah. I think from Mozilla's
perspective, like we don't have
shareholders, right? We're not trying to
make gobs and gobs of money. The
Mozilla mission and what we are here to
do at the end of the day is to create a
better internet and one that works for
people and that's open, accessible for
all, right? And sure, it is very
convenient for big tech companies to
have a royalty-free codec for video
streaming so they don't have to pay
anybody, but they totally could pay,
right? What Mozilla's angle here is to
make these formats and make these
changes in a way that really empowers
everybody and obviously that empower
that creates economic value for
everybody and some people capture that
more than others. I think from Mozilla's
perspective, we want to be able to
continue to exist and that does mean
that we have to think about revenue. And
at the moment, you know, a lot of
Mozilla's revenue comes from one of the
dominant advertising players on the
internet, which is Google. And so we
would like to change that, but it's
hard. And it's particularly hard because
it's not necessarily where our heart is,
right? Our heart is around having impact
on the internet and making that better.
And so it is a tension that I think does
exist between within Mozilla of you know
how much to focus on one and how much to
focus on the other. But I think that
Mozilla at its best you know we have
some necessary business stuff that we
have to manage. But the end goal of what
Mozilla is about is having this impact
that benefits everyone. So then after
these examples of uh distinguished
engineers, I'm curious what advice you
would give to someone who wants to
become a distinguished engineer.
>> In terms of one thing that I think that
basically everybody can work on at
whatever level they are is writing. This
is a particular hobby horse for me
because I think that this was an area
where Mozilla and myself included did
not have a lot of developed capability
and I think it is one of the most
powerful things. We have this internal
memo which is actually you know public
on the internet um directed at Mozilla
uh engineers called writing things down.
And one of the things that this memo
does is it makes the case that writing
is both about the artifact that you
produce, which is useful for
coordination and wide review and getting
feedback, but also
useful in the process itself. And that
is because the process of writing is the
process of thinking and refining your
ideas and articulating them. And this is
just an infinite game that you can
always get better at. And I think it is
one of the most powerful ways to create
clarity of thinking for yourself because
clarity of thinking is in my view one of
the most important things. And you only
can really get that by forcing yourself
to write down your ideas. And so I
suppose one, you know, pertinent or
timely piece of advice is if you care
about this, do not use an LLM to produce
text for YouTube. Um because first of
all, if you're putting your name on this
thing, at least today the LM's like it's
pretty easy to tell when somebody does
that. But more importantly, you are
losing the opportunity to do the
thinking yourself. And that thinking
that happens when you write is one of
the most important types of thinking for
growth.
>> Do you have tips on how to write well?
>> Yes. Um,
I would say
one of the most important things is that
it doesn't need to be any longer
than what you have to say. I think I
always prefer shorter documents and I
think there's some notion where people
run out of things to say and at that
point you either
need to refine your ideas more or you're
just done. And it's never useful to
anybody to add fluff. And dealing with
documents that are fluffy and overly
over rot is one of my least favorite
things.
So, I think that's one piece
related to that. I think that it's
important to focus on substance rather
than rhetoric, which is sort of related
to fluff. But I think that some people
say, "Oh, well, I'm not uh a native
English speaker, and therefore I'm never
going to be able to write as beautifully
as others." And I think that's the wrong
way to think about it. Like there is
some basic baseline that you need to
work on in terms of articulation of the
ideas but
it is not about using the most flowery
words. It is about clarity of thought
and clarity of thought once you have it
is relatively easy to express in written
form if you practice.
>> Yeah. I think every single person I've
ever asked this question to has always
said be concise. It's shocking to me how
uh unanimous that advice is. Okay. So
going back to the browser wars, I think
we all know how things have played out
and I see that there's this new era of
browser wars that's things are heating
up again. There's a lot of competition
for an AI browser or bringing AI into
existing browsers and I'm kind of
curious for your take on what the future
of the browser wars is going to look
like as the CTO of Firefox. So I think
one thing that's really worth clearing
up is that you hear that there's, you
know, every month you hear about a new
browser from this AI company or that.
And what I think is really important to
understand is that these are not
browsers as I think of browsers. These
are different frontends, different
window dressing and monetization keys on
top of Chrome
because much of what powers a browser is
the browser engine. And browser engines
are also extremely complicated and
difficult to build. And there have been
fewer and fewer browser engines as time
goes on. And today Firefox is the only
independent browser that has no
dependency on a browser engine from
somebody else. So you've got Safari
which is pretty vertically integrated
with WebKit. Nobody else really uses
WebKit directly. Um then you've got
Firefox where we build Firefox with
Gecko underneath it. And then you've got
Chrome on top of Chromium and all these
other browsers like Opera and Perplexity
and even Edge. uh they all use Chromium
under the hood because what they're
seeking to do is not necessarily to
evolve the web platform and the web
experience. They are trying to
control the touch point with the
consumer in this world that is coming
with AI because on desktop the way
consumers experience the internet is
through their browser and everybody is
jockeying over what this experience is
going to look like and people want to
control that experience. So I am very
much of the opinion that AI is coming to
consumer technology like water running
downhill and that this is not something
that is going to be stopped or reversed
because there is so much disruptive
potential of the technology.
But where that water goes and how it
ends up, it can end up over here in
somebody's reservoir or it can end up in
the ocean or it can end up as a river.
There are lots of opportunities now to
steer how it plays out. And there is
also a lot of desire for people to
capture it for themselves. And Chrome,
as an example, is making a very
aggressive play to control the AI stack
by leveraging its dominance in Chrome.
And they're doing this at multiple
levels. They're obviously doing it as
part of the Chrome browser where there's
5,000 different integrations with Gemini
as part of Chrome now. But they're also
doing it as part of the web platform.
They are advancing some proprietary APIs
that we do not support to allow websites
to have local to access to an LLM inside
of the browser. And this is attractive
to web authors because it allows you to
offload your compute and you don't have
to pay for the inference and you can
just ask the browser to do the
inference. But the thing that is
different about this from other web
standards is that there is no way to
specify
an LLM or to have it have deterministic
behavior that is interoperable. And so
the API calls that you have into this
LLM are fundamentally unspecified. But
as the owner of the world's dominant web
browser, they have a lot of market power
to get websites to tune their usage of
the LLM to what Gemini expects. And
there is obviously a co-evolution of AI
experiences and the models underneath
them. and creating a world where more
and more AI experiences are built on top
of Gemini is part of Google's strategy
to achieve and dominate control of the
space. And we at Mozilla are not
building our own foundation model. We
don't have any particular horse in the
race. But what we are trying to do is to
make sure that the space remains open in
the web that the way that the web has
been open and that users have choice of
how they integrate with these things and
which ones they use and also that the
web remains important and relevant
because there is a big risk that the web
becomes a backend detail that's used by
rag from your chat GPT query or that's
used by operator on the back end where
it is no longer the focal point of the
user's experience. But if this were to
happen, there would be much that would
be lost because the web is a very unique
system in the sense that it provides
users agency and control that they would
not necessarily achieve elsewhere.
Right? It is not a direct experience
that is produced and delivered in a way
that can't be modified. It is
reinterpretable content that the browser
can modify and render as the user
chooses. Right? Right? And there are
lots of ways that this matters in
practice. You know, things like ad
blockers are a great example of how the
reinterpretable nature of the web allows
users to control their experiences in
important ways. And that the web is a
safe environment where it's safe to open
a link even from an untrusted source.
And that all of this is not created and
controlled by any one company, but that
it is built as an interoperable system
where anybody who produces code that
implements the right protocols can show
up and be part of the system. And this
leads to a multistakeholder environment
where no single entity controls the
evolution of the web platform. And that
is not how most platforms happen, right?
It's not how the platforms happen before
the web and it's not how you know the
native mobile platforms happen after the
web. It is in some sense a very
historical accident that we got
something that is this
well aligned with the vision that
Mozilla has for how the internet should
work and it's very important to us to
make sure that the changes that happen
with AI do not sacrifice these
properties.
>> You mentioned all the components of the
browser and there's the web engine and
you know a lot of those AI browsers and
um like and also other ones like Opera
etc. they actually built on Chromium at
the end. I'm curious what what do you
think would happen if Firefox was built
on Chromium? Like what is the advantage
of Firefox building its own uh web
engine?
So it's a lot of work and we like doing
hard things. But the strategic advantage
from the perspective of Mozilla's
mission is that it gives Mozilla a seat
at the table when web standards and the
future of the web is decided. And it
used to be the case that standards
bodies were wide groups of many
different vendors. You know, you had
Opera back in there with its own engine.
You had Internet Explorer, you had
Safari, you had Mozilla. And as time has
gone on, engines have dropped off the
map because if you look at it from a
bottom line perspective, there's
basically no justification for doing it.
It is a giant cost center um from a
business perspective. But from a mission
perspective, the benefits of being part
of the conversations that shape the web
are profound. And that is why Mozilla is
the last independent player that is
doing it because we are not driven by
that bottom line. We're driven by the
impact. And so imagine if there was a
world where there was no Firefox at the
standards table. You would have Apple
running WebKit and you would have Google
in charge of everything else. And Apple
and Google, very um capable and
innovative companies do not get along
particularly well and are very
entrenched in their own interests. And
in a bilateral environment, as you can
even see in the mobile space, there is a
sense of
entrenchment that can prevent progress.
And one unique thing that Mozilla brings
to the table, even though we have
relatively small smaller market share
compared to these other browsers, is
that we bring a fresh perspective and
the ability to tilt the conversation
back towards what is best for the user
and what is best for the web.
One example that I'm particularly proud
of is not necessarily one of web
standards discussions per se. These
happen all the time in working groups
all over. The you know uh editor of the
HTML specification is a Mozilla employee
who works with everybody and continuing
to refine um HTML.
But the example that I would go to is
actually one about performance. So, it's
long been the case that competition is
what drives the advancement of browsers
getting faster. And it is just this
amazing achievement that browsers
continually get faster, right? It's like
the semiconductor supply chain. It's
something that people don't even think
about. And just like every year, the
stuff underneath that is powering all
the experiences getting faster and
faster.
And the thing if you look at the
history, the thing that makes browsers
get faster is competition from other
browsers. And the way this has
historically been measured is that
different browsers would produce a
benchmark that they would design in a
way that was, you know, particularly
well suited for their engine and then
they would optimize it and then other
browsers would say, well, yes, that's
your private cooked benchmark. And there
was an initiative a couple years ago
around this benchmark called speedometer
3 to try and produce a shared benchmark
that we could all agree on that would be
representative not of just what worked
well in any particular browser but would
be representative of the web and the
experiences that we wanted to get
faster. And this is a type of engagement
where if you just have the bilateral
relationship between Google and Apple,
it would predictably go nowhere because
there is just too there are too many
opportunities for somebody to tilt it in
their own interests in a way that the
other side says, "Aha, I see what you're
doing there." But I think that Mozilla's
involvement was really critical in
keeping everybody focused on the stated
mission of the operation which was not
to make any particular browser look good
but to provide us a shared incentive to
make browser engines faster together in
order to make the web faster. And
in
Firefox, the impact has been pretty
incredible uh of what
the of what has been driven by this
benchmark over the last couple years. I
think that really across all of the
browsers
at least Firefox and Chrome both Firefox
and Chrome have improved their score on
the benchmark by a factor of two. So
have gotten twice as fast and the we
have actually measured in Firefox the
impact that this has translated to on
real world performance on the same
machines in terms of page load um and
time to first paint and all these things
and it's on the order of 30%. So I think
it is reasonable to say that having this
benchmark has made the web 30% faster
and that is something that benefits
everyone and I don't think it's
something that would have happened
without Mozilla in the room.
Coming to the end of the interview, I
just want to ask you a few questions
kind of reflecting over your career
because I feel like you have a lot of
experience. When you look back on your
career and you know, you made a lot of
contributions. You were an IC through
and through for almost all of your time
at Mozilla. I'm curious, is there any
technical decision that in hindsight you
wish you'd change? One thing that comes
to mind is a situation
where I think the outcome, the technical
outcome was good, but I think in some
sense the process wasn't worth it. And
this was around web render, which was
the graphics backend in servo. When I
was working on quantum CSS to take the
servo CSS engine and put it in Firefox,
I was very excited about the momentum of
uplifting other parts of the rendering
pipeline of Servo into Firefox. And I
advocated very heavily that the graphics
team should replace its rendering and
rasterization pipeline with the one from
Servo. And
this was not based on technical
expertise on my part around it. It was
very much a vibes thing of this is where
it's going. And that vibes thing was
infectious. And I was not necessarily
strictly in a decision-m point at this
time. But there were I think that point
of view really caught on um with
management and I remember there was uh
the the basic issue was that the team
many engineers on the team had very
strong doubts about this. They thought
that it was not ready, that it was too
much, um that it was a very risky
project. And they tried to express some
of these concerns and there was a
engineering leader at the time who heard
them and responded with C++ is not the
future. And
that vibes-based enthusiasm for
a risky technical direction over the
concerns of the people who knew it the
best ended up being very toxic and a
number of our most senior and most
impactful graphics engineers ended up
leaving. Now the rest of the team ended
up rallying and web render did turn out
to be a major and difficult and
expensive and manyear project. The
actual technical result is awesome. It
is a fantastic uh engine and it is
really performant and safe and does all
these great things and I'm really proud
of the team for what they built. But I
think that pushing it on the team when
the team wasn't ready and wasn't aligned
on it had collateral damage that I
regret.
>> Is there a top book that made an impact
on your career? I would consider myself
to be an avid reader, but the truth is
um I don't read a lot of books. Uh I do
read some, but honestly, you know, the
the books that I can think of that
probably have had the most profound
impact on my thinking are not books that
I've actually read. Uh and that's just a
personal style of mine. Uh I tend to be
very wide in terms of what I consume and
reading a whole book on a topic is a
depth first approach. And I certainly
wouldn't want anybody to take this as
encouragement not to read books, but uh
and I think that there's a lot of value
that can be gained from that and it's
something that many people do and do
very successfully. But it's not the only
way. I think you know there was this
book that I just read a book review of
called good good strategy bad strategy
and I just read three pages and that has
just stuck with me as a description of
like what is wrong of many strategy what
is wrong with many strategy documents
that I read um just a very clear and
crisp articulation of the muddle that
gets created and what the right thing
looks like and that's something I never
actually read the book I just read a
three-page summary
um other I think ideas that have had a
profound impact on me from books book
turn the ship around which I also
haven't read which is about empowering
teams on the subject we just discussed
um innovator's dilemma Clayton
Christensen I think it's very powerful
analysis of how the industry works
I definitely do like to consume content
from a lot of different areas I really
encourage people to look wide not just
within tech
within tech you know I I do really
appreciate Ben Thompson's writing. I
think is really good um for
understanding the tech industry, but I
like to also spend a lot of time
consuming uh writing from other
intellectual disciplines. One example is
I've found that the whole geopolitics,
national security um space is an area
where there's actually a lot of
thoughtful writing that I had never been
exposed to. And there are people who
basically spend their lives really
thinking about what happens on a
battlefield and what goes well and what
doesn't. And a lot of those ideas
actually translate very similarly or you
know it certainly rhymes with situations
um you know when battles between big
tech and how do you manage and motivate
teams and so I would definitely
encourage people to take a wide view of
the thought that is out there because
there are many things that can be
learned uh from things that are outside
of just tech and business.
>> Last question for you is if you could
give yourself some advice when you had
just entered the industry, is there
anything you'd say knowing everything
you know now?
>> At the end of the day, to be humble is
the most important. I think that I had a
particular attitude not strictly about
myself, but about engineering and the
role of engineers and how important
engineers were. And there was definitely
this attitude of that was the center of
the universe. And as I've gone on, I've
started to realize that there are many
other important things that go and you
know that I you don't necessarily
understand when you're first starting
out at an organization of why there are
certain processes and why there are
certain functions and what do we need a
legal team for and all these kinds of
things. And as I've progressed and found
myself more in a leadership role, I have
really managed to develop an
appreciation and empathy for all of the
different players within the
organization and within the industry and
realizing that everybody has a point of
view and a place that they're coming
from. and that working to understand
where people are coming from is the way
to make progress.
>> All right. Well, thank you Bobby for
your time. I really appreciate it. With
that being said, is there any last words
you want to say for the audience?
>> Yeah, I think the most important message
I want to send is that the web very much
matters and the web is something that
underpins so much of what we do. And I
think for a lot of people it is
invisible in something that they take
for granted, right? It is like water
flowing through the taps or the
semiconductor supply chain of this
amazing resource that continues to get
better over time and continues to
deliver us more value that we take for
granted. But it doesn't have to be that
way and it easily could not. And we
could easily backslide into a situation
of unilateral control by big tech over
the experiences that people have. And I
think that simply losing focus on
something because we've had it so good
for so long would be a tragedy. And I
encourage people to think about what
they gain from the existence of an open
and free web and to participate in
trying doing your best to keep it open.
And you know, from a selfish perspective
and from the perspective of the web, a
great thing that you can do if you are
building websites and experiences is
making sure that they work in all
browsers and that you don't do the lazy
path and build something that only works
in Google Chrome because that is the
first step to ending us back in a
situation where we were 25 years ago.
>> Thanks for listening to the podcast. I
don't sell anything or do sponsorships,
but if you want to help out with the
podcast, you can support by engaging
with the content on YouTube or on
Spotify if you want to drop a review,
that'll be super helpful. And if there's
any guests that you want to bring on to,
please let me know. I feel like sourcing
very senior IC's, there's no wellstudied
list out there on Google that I can just
search this up. So, if there's someone
in your org or at your company who you
really look up to and you want to hear
their career story, let me know and I'll
reach out to